<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Calgary Urbanite</title>
    <description>CalgaryUrbanite is an urban / sustainability / social / web blogazine.
</description>
    <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://calgaryurbanite.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 21:41:24 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 21:41:24 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Keystone XL: If It Fails, Who To Blame?</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;h1&quot;&gt;Keystone XL:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;h2&quot;&gt;If It Fails, Who To Blame?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;quad leftedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fancy&quot;&gt;Let me take you forward in time:&lt;/span&gt; the Keystone XL pipeline decision from the US has finally come. And it&#39;s not good. Headlines across the country report on the news. They describe the news as &quot;devastating&quot;, our relationship with the United States as &quot;broken&quot;. Sun News uses a font size so large on the front page of their papers they struggle to fit in 5 letters. Twitter is ablaze with nothing but ugly words for the US, Obama, &quot;envirofacists&quot; and Tom Mulcair. The American anthem is booed at NHL games across the country - or at least in Alberta. Canadians across the country will be more united than their usual divided selves in blaming everyone and everything for their failure to sell their oil - something that should quite simply sell it self. The only ones managing to avoid the blame will be The Harper Government&amp;trade;. They will use the news as this sort of &quot;fossil-fuel 9/11&quot; to shore up more support for their agenda to do whatever it takes to sell oil elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the present. Regardless if that scenario comes to fruition, the one thing I do know is that the Harper government shouldn&#39;t be able to avoid the blame for the Keystone XL situation, they should be at the centre of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Keystone XL pipeline should probably be built. It makes a lot of sense for Canada and the US. We don&#39;t seem to have any interest in doing much of our own oil refining, so this is a way to avoid that problem and make a quick buck off our bitumen. The US needs oil, preferably from a reliable neighbour and they can secure more energy for a rebounding economy. The Athabasca oil sands have become, unfairly so, somewhat of a world scape-goat for carbon emissions. They are definitely a beast, and something that should have been grown smartly, not rapidly-above-all-else like they are now, but the idealist in me still thinks we can turn things around for the better over time. As a Canadian observer, it is frustrating to watch the United States protest our oil sands. Its emissions are a drop in the bucket compared to their own coal projects, which unfortunately most of their citizens have put a blind eye to. &quot;Blame Canada&quot; I suppose, it&#39;s just easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But us Canadians, really should blame ourselves. The United States is very aware of our environmental record as of late, even if most Canadians are not. They&#39;ve seen that&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ctvnews.ca/politics/documents-reveal-pipeline-industry-drove-changes-to-navigable-waters-act-1.1164476&quot;&gt;we&#39;ve ripped up our environmental laws left, right and centre&lt;/a&gt;. They&#39;ve seen that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestar.com/opinion/editorials/2013/03/18/harper_governments_reckless_and_undemocratic_muzzling_of_scientists_editorial.html&quot;&gt;we&#39;ve prevented our scientists from speaking up about their work&lt;/a&gt;. They&#39;ve seen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/closing-of-experimental-lakes-area-called-a-travesty-as-feds-move-to-dismantle-buildings/article9846568/&quot;&gt;we&#39;ve gutted our environmental research projects&lt;/a&gt;. They&#39;ve seen that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2011/12/04/pol-durban-canada.html&quot;&gt;we&#39;ve stonewalled climate change debate on the international stage&lt;/a&gt;. These are deliberate choices the Harper government has made and its supporters endorse. Criticism of these choices is openly mocked. Remember those &#39;Fossil of the Day&#39; awards Canada racked up at climate conferences? The awards themselves may not even be that deserving or accurate, but it doesn&#39;t matter - the world has seen our reaction to the awards, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/ElizabethMayGreenLeader/posts/182863368473229&quot;&gt;how we&#39;ve laughed at them, or even relished receiving them&lt;/a&gt;. And you know what? That reaction drives opposition towards us. The same opposition &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/us-protest-paints-keystone-as-emissions-villain/article8774981/&quot;&gt;protesting the US government to shut us out&lt;/a&gt;. We&#39;ve marginalized ourselves because we&#39;ve marginalized every one we disagree with. We&#39;ve shown very well that we don&#39;t care what any of our opponents have to say about us. It&#39;s the same attitude we see from nations like North Korea, and Iran (albeit on a smaller scale) and look how much value they&#39;re getting out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Keystone XL decision should never have been such a close call, and it certainly wouldn&#39;t have been if not for the unnecessarily cavalier attitudes of the Harper government. If Keystone is approved, and nothing I mentioned above comes to pass, I hope we still realize we must work with our opponents, not brazingly defy them. We need to be an ally for the environment, not just to help fight the greatest challenge of our time, but also to ensure we continue to be a nation that the rest of the world wants to do business with. And for heaven&#39;s sake we need to diversify our economy! I don&#39;t think I need to explain to anyone why our national economy should not live and die by individual pipelines carrying non-renewable resources. It is imperative we create a future more resiliant than our present, and that means listening to our critics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;quotes&quot; class=&quot;double rightedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;quote1&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;As a Canadian observer, it is frustrating to watch the United States protest our oil sands.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;quote2&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&#39;ve marginalized ourselves because we&#39;ve marginalized every one we disagree with.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;quote3&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We need to be an ally for the environment, not just to help fight the greatest challenge of our time, but also to ensure we continue to be a nation that the rest of the world wants to do business with.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2013/03/18/keystone-xl-if-it-fails.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2013/03/18/keystone-xl-if-it-fails.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Engineering - The Greatest Threat Ever</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;newtitle two quad&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;h1&quot;&gt;Social Engineering&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;h2&quot;&gt;The Greatest Threat To Our Society Ever?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;two quad&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dark times are upon us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our society is being hijacked by extremists who wish to impose their dangerous way of life on us by means of expensive social-engineering experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, before I get carried away with this, I&#39;ll admit I&#39;m playing devil&#39;s advocate here, please bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bike lanes are destroying our city. How dare we sink tens, even hundreds of thousands of dollars into constructing a few lanes around the city including a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/calgary/story/2013/02/25/calgary-cycle-track-downtown-calgary.html&quot;&gt;single median-separated track in the city&lt;/a&gt; to service the commute of an increasing number of Calgarians? This is a text-book example of social engineering, that is, the government is trying to change how we as Calgarians live our lives by incentivizing some wacky new life style. I won&#39;t stand for it. The Car&amp;trade; is the only way to get around in Calgary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot; src=&quot;/file/post/20130301/social-engineering-threat/closet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Closet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Observe what a closet might look like if it were owned by militant extremists hellbent on destroying the foundations of society as we know it through their fold-up bicycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another dangerous experiment being imposed on us by big government? &lt;strong&gt;Density&lt;/strong&gt;. Just like we like our cars, we like our big houses, big back yards and our privacy. Why would the government start forcing Calgary to build up and not out? We don&#39;t need politicians telling our developers how to develop, we instead need the free-market to reign! Again, density, is just another extremist social engineering experiment, one that will destroy Calgarians&#39; way of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calgary is a sprawling, car-happy city, and our glorious free-market has made it this way not government subsidy. We don&#39;t need government to fight the free-market by wasting our tax dollars to subsidize a dense, bicycle friendly city that very few of us would actually want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;h2&quot;&gt;Wait, what&#39;s that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, I&#39;m done playing the role of a foaming-at-the-mouth news site commentator. It was fun but now I feel dirty. &lt;strong&gt;Here are the facts&lt;/strong&gt;. Government &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; using our taxes on massive social-engineering experiments. &lt;strong&gt;Big time&lt;/strong&gt;. But it&#39;s not bike-lanes or density that is the culprit, but rather car-friendly urban sprawl. Urban sprawl is only able to exist through massive government subsidy from all three levels of government. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The federal government has ripped up environmental legislation to encourage oil development that increases supply and lowers cost. There&#39;s no price on pollution so we are essentially borrowing money from our future generations who will need to clean up the mess in order to keep oil prices artificially low in the present.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmontonjournal.com/business/Home+builders+fume+over+Canada+Post/8025747/story.html&quot;&gt;Canada post can barely afford to service new communities&lt;/a&gt; and are realizing they can&#39;t subsidize that sprawl any more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The City of Calgary subsidizes the sprawl by stretching transit to these far away communities, paying most costs associated with getting water, power, police and fire coverage to the sprawl, and spends hundreds of millions on building and maintaining all the roads for the sprawl to keep Calgary &#39;car-friendly&#39;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The amount of taxes going to roads over bicycle infrastructure &lt;a href=&quot;http://bikecalgary.org/faq&quot;&gt;is disproportional&lt;/a&gt; to the number of commuters cycling instead of driving - disproportionate in favour of drivers of course. The costs of bike infrastructure seem to get negative press, but as Portland has seen, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.politifact.com/oregon/statements/2011/mar/19/sam-adams/portland-mayor-sam-adams-says-portlands-spent-its-/&quot;&gt;their entire bike infrastructure budget cost about as much as a mile of highway&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the free-market wants sprawl and the car infrastructure to support it, why is it so heavily subsidized? The simple answer is that the free-market doesn&#39;t want it as much as we think it does. Sprawl has been perhaps the largest and most expensive social engineering experiment of all time, and unlike experimenting with density and pedestrian and cycling friendly infrastructure, the sprawl experiment is failing. Car infrastructure and sprawl are only able to appear as attractive as they currently do because subsidy keeps them from playing on a level field with density and pedestrian/cycling infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not that we shouldn&#39;t ban growth outwards in favour of upwards, but we should all recognize that it isn&#39;t density that&#39;s the social experiment, it has been sprawl, and it&#39;s now time to level the playing field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2013/03/01/social-engineering-threat.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2013/03/01/social-engineering-threat.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts From Another Armchair Quarterback of Occupy Calgary</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;two quad&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20111116/occupy-calgary/occupy.png&quot; alt=&quot;Occupy Calgary&quot; /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;It&#39;s time the City of Calgary kicked the bums out!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This knee-jerk reaction to Occupy Calgary and others like it are common. It&#39;s a popular viewpoint, and with good reason. It&#39;s easy to want a protest of squatting in Olympic Plaza removed as hastily as possible when you read stories of public defecation, drug use, tent burning accidents and above all else when individuals from the movement make statements reeking of entitlement such as demanding the city supply power and heating. If that&#39;s all to the story (and despite &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.calgaryherald.com/2011/11/08/the-results-are-in-the-answer-is-10/&quot;&gt;seemingly more media on hand reporting the story than people actually sleeping in tents&lt;/a&gt;, that&#39;s all the story ever seems to be) I&#39;d get behind the knee-jerk reactions. But it isn&#39;t all to the story, not by a long shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occupy Calgary stems from Occupy Wall Street, a movement started in September to camp out in the financial heart of the United States and make a very strong statement: the middle class is pissed off. They have every right to be with high rates of unemployment (especially amongst youth), hundreds of billions of dollars from tax payers given back to the corporations that failed them and fueled a housing crisis, record budget deficits, extensions to tax-cuts for America&#39;s most wealthy. With the middle class taking an obvious backseat to a wealthy elite (it has gotten so absurd that&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/10/30/tax-the-poor-conservative-plan-occupy-wall-street_n_1064685.html&quot;&gt;Republicans propose taxing the poor instead of the rich&lt;/a&gt;), unprecedented amounts of middle-class working Americans supported the Occupy Wall Street protest. &quot;We are the 99%&quot; had real percievable meaning and I imagine it knocked a lot of people off their seat. Despite being leaderless with few cohesive demands, the movement has showed that many Americans are no longer willing to sit quiet about the economic reality fostered by government that caters to the wealthy minority. In an era of apathy, that is a powerful statement, demands or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canadians seemed to be in strong support of Occupy Wall Street, at least before it came to our home. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vancouverobserver.com/world/canada/2011/10/13/finance-minister-sympathizes-occupywallst-protesters&quot;&gt;Finance Minister Jim Flaherty initially expressed sympathy for Occupy Wall Street&lt;/a&gt;, but that&#39;s unlikely to be the case now. After all, why would Canadians be upset with the current economic situation when we have the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cba.ca/en/media-room/65-news-releases/536-good-news-for-all-canadians-world-economic-forum-again-ranks-canadas-banks-as-the-worlds-soundest-&quot;&gt;soundest financial institutions in the world&lt;/a&gt;? It&#39;s not like we have record deficits, high unemployment, a government looking to further deregulate our economy (that weathered the storm better than anywhere due to an era of stronger regulation) or a large and getting larger gap between the rich and the poor. Okay, I lied, we do have all those things, but admittedly despite the negative trends we are better off than our neighbours to the south, so we should probably all just shut out traps. I am glad that not all of us are however, as every day there&#39;s a story that justifies the Occupy movement. A great example is the recent deal reached by the City of Edmonton to build a new arena for the Oilers. Edmontonians will be paying a billionaire millions of dollars to build a new arena, &lt;a href=&quot;http://daveberta.ca/2011/10/why-would-the-government-of-alberta-help-fund-the-proposed-katz-group-arena/&quot;&gt;while the billionaire will pay back the city back in 30 years&lt;/a&gt;. The public absorbs the risk, and the billionaire takes the profits - but the Occupy movement has nothing to be upset about, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the only debate now coming out of the Occupy Calgary movement is whether the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms trumps Calgary bylaws against camping in parks or vice versa. While an interesting exercise, it&#39;s not the debate that needs to be had. With this in mind, I&#39;ve called for a peaceful and voluntary end of the Occupy Calgary movement. These are the issues of a generation, and they will not be settled by a park camp out. Raising awareness is a large victory in itself and with that many whom were eager to participate in the movement or just be in support it have left or stood down respectively, not because the issues are any less important but because they are no longer the focus in the minds of Calgarians. The remains of Occupy Calgary in Olympic Plaza appear to be full-time activists and those in poor mental health, likely with nowhere else to be. The average middle class Calgarian has gone home, and with it mainstream support. The opponents of the Occupy movement are now free to move in and show it as not representative of the middle class but rather as a fringe, extremist movement. I understand why there are opponents: many have it good and think there&#39;s no reason others can&#39;t have it good too. They see Occupiers and their ilk as lazy, and unwilling to make something of themselves. Perhaps many are (I certainly have little sympathy for full-time activists taking up each and every cause as if there isn&#39;t a single issue they wouldn&#39;t clash with authority on), but it is here where I wish to make what I hope is my strongest point: I understand why some want to exercise a supposed superiority over others by boasting of their hard work, education etc. &lt;strong&gt;but simply saying &#39;get a job&#39; does no one any favours&lt;/strong&gt;. We do not live in a world where every one has the same access to higher education, the same networking opportunities, or getting more basic: the same healthy meals, the same safe homes to be raised in and the same mental health. As repulsed as I am by a fringe few demanding the city provide them heaters at Olympic Plaza, I&#39;m just as repulsed by those going to Olympic Plaza to film these disadvantaged few. Yes, if you provoke a debate you came prepared for with someone suffering from a drug addiction, or a mental disorder, you&#39;re likely to win. Congratulations. Squatting in Olympic Plaza is a problem, but telling the disadvantaged to get jobs brings us no closer to ending the camp out, nor does it diminish the real issues at hand by the Occupy movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I have wanted Occupy Calgary to end in its current form, I don&#39;t support the knee-jerk reaction so many are standing behind. Mayor Nenshi, the City of Calgary and our by-law and police enforcement have all done an exemplary job of not &#39;kicking the bums out&#39; but maintaining the balancing act of freedom of expression and public safety. No matter where you stand on Occupy Calgary and the Occupy movement, tact and balance, not knee-jerk reactions and violence, are the answer to a peaceful outcome - and that is truly what the 99% want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/11/16/occupy-calgary.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/11/16/occupy-calgary.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Notion Of A Left Leaning News Media Is Dead</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;double leftedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to be popular conception that news media in Canada has a &quot;liberal bias&quot;, that is, it&#39;s friendly to so-called &quot;liberal&quot; beliefs and those who uphold them, even at the expense of purely objective truth. It may not be so obvious, often rather a subtle, almost subliminal bias. As a news-addict, reading far too much every day, I&#39;m here to say that any notion of a left-leaning news-media is dead. Those that say otherwise aren&#39;t being honest, because afterall, everyone wants to play the role of the underdog, even when they&#39;re not.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Remember this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;quad rightedge left&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/GrliDQs1Jps&quot; width=&quot;620&quot; height=&quot;495&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;double leftedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the day I realized our left-leaning news-media was a myth. This interview was a few days before the election, and CTV chose to skewer Liberal leader Stephane Dion. They lied to him. Stephane Dion asked if he could start over, to which the interviewer said yes. But they didn&#39;t start over, as the entire interview was aired. Even though the question (&#39;what would you do then if you were leader now?&#39;) was even more broken than Mr. Dion&#39;s answer, the result was politically damaging, and CTV violated any notion of journalistic ethics to make sure it aired. This isn&#39;t the stuff of a news-media that&#39;s &quot;left-leaning&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;double column left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now &amp;nbsp;it wasn&#39;t always this way. I certainly remember when the news-media inserted subtle and not-so-subtle jabs against &quot;the right&quot;. Observe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110810/left-leaning-news-medias-dead/harper_government.300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;double rightedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this example, from over five years ago, isn&#39;t remotely as concerning as the bias behind the Dion clip years later from the same news organization. Chalk the stupidity of that parliament-on-fire picture up to the same mentality that causes photographers and editors to think it&#39;s clever to use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.ca/search?tbm=isch&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;source=hp&amp;amp;biw=1599&amp;amp;bih=829&amp;amp;q=presidential+halo+behind+presidents&amp;amp;gbv=2&amp;amp;oq=presidential+halo+behind+presidents&amp;amp;aq=f&amp;amp;aqi=&amp;amp;aql=&amp;amp;gs_sm=s&amp;amp;gs_upl=1198l1198l0l1530l1l1l0l0l0l0l205l205l2-1l1l0&quot;&gt;background as a halo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, five years have passed and news-media in Canada has shifted far away from any indication of so-called left-leanings. Just take a look at newspaper endorsements in the 2008 and 2011 federal elections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;quad leftedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;table style=&quot;width: 640px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110810/left-leaning-news-medias-dead/2008.png&quot; alt=&quot;2008 Election Endorsements&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Conservatives                                                                      
&lt;ul style=&quot;line-height: 1.1;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.northpeel.com/editorial/57696&quot;&gt;The Brampton Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brantfordexpositor.ca/ArticleDisplay.aspx?e=1243512&quot;&gt;Brantford Expositor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canada.com/calgaryherald/news/theeditorialpage/story.html?id=cbe1aa30-8dcb-4aa6-b4ec-3562532fc1ac&quot;&gt;Calgary Herald&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://calsun.canoe.ca/Comment/POV/2008/10/12/7058606-sun.html&quot;&gt;Calgary Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dailygleaner.canadaeast.com/opinion/article/446078&quot;&gt;The Daily Gleaner&amp;nbsp;(Fredericton)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/opinion/displaystory.cfm?story_id=12381439&quot;&gt;The Economist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canada.com/edmontonjournal/news/opinion/story.html?id=f8ce79aa-db37-4c7a-8c43-4c8d37aa6f38&quot;&gt;Edmonton Journal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmontonsun.com/Comment/Commentary/2008/10/12/7060476-sun.html&quot;&gt;Edmonton Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canada.com/montrealgazette/news/editorial/story.html?id=842b61df-7004-4cfb-9f61-513309031805&quot;&gt;The Gazette&amp;nbsp;(Montreal)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20081009.weelection2008/BNStory/politics&quot;&gt;The Globe and Mail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://network.nationalpost.com/np/blogs/fullcomment/archive/2008/10/08/national-post-editorial-board-a-conservative-majority-serves-canada-s-needs.aspx&quot;&gt;National Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ottawasun.com/Comment/home.html&quot;&gt;Ottawa Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canada.com/theprovince/news/editorial/story.html?id=b70c9ee77de8-4a7a-a649-58706fa0d773&quot;&gt;The Province&amp;nbsp;(Vancouver)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recorder.ca/ArticleDisplay.aspx?e=1243064&quot;&gt;The Recorder and Times&amp;nbsp;(Brockville)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.torontosun.com/comment/editorial/&quot;&gt;Toronto Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.therecord.com/article/426593&quot;&gt;Waterloo Region Record&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canada.com/vancouversun/news/editorial/story.html?id=8b900721-0cb2-428a-aaaa-18bd722f5a3d&quot;&gt;The Vancouver Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.canada.com/windsorstar/news/editorial/story.html?id=43a98233-5383-4bc4-b63a-6f41c8673851&quot;&gt;Windsor Star&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.winnipegfreepress.com/editorial/story/4237418p-4880617c.html&quot;&gt;Winnipeg Free Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.winnipegsun.com/Comment/Editorial/2008/10/12/7057401-sun.html&quot;&gt;Winnipeg Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Others                                                              
&lt;ul style=&quot;line-height: 1.1;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestar.com/FederalElection/article/515895&quot;&gt;Toronto Star&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ubyssey.ca/?p=4942&quot;&gt;The Ubyssey&amp;nbsp;(U of BC)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ledevoir.com/2008/10/11/210210.html&quot;&gt;Le Devoir&amp;nbsp;(Montreal)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nowtoronto.com/news/story.cfm?content=165335&quot;&gt;Now&amp;nbsp;(Toronto)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110810/left-leaning-news-medias-dead/2011.png&quot; alt=&quot;2011 Election Endorsements&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Conservatives                                                  
&lt;ul style=&quot;line-height: 1.1;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bramptonguardian.com/opinion/editorial/article/998658--editorial-harper-deserves-a-majority&quot;&gt;The Brampton Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recorder.ca/ArticleDisplay.aspx?e=3102322&quot;&gt;The Recorder and Times&amp;nbsp;(Brockville)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.insidehalton.com/opinion/editorial/article/998870--our-choice-on-may-2&quot;&gt;Burlington Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calgaryherald.com/opinion/Tories+deserve+majority/4703001/story.html?cid=megadrop_story&quot;&gt;Calgary Herald&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calgarysun.com/2011/04/30/sun-backs-stephen-harper&quot;&gt;Calgary Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/node/18620784?story_id=18620784&amp;amp;fsrc=rss&quot;&gt;The Economist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmontonjournal.com/opinion/editorials/winning+formula+Alberta+voters/4702450/story.html&quot;&gt;Edmonton Journal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmontonsun.com/2011/04/30/sun-backs-stephen-harper&quot;&gt;Edmonton Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.insidetoronto.com/opinion/editorial/article/999234--editorial-conservative-majority-best-for-canada&quot;&gt;Etobicoke Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/opinions/editorials/the-globes-election-endorsement-facing-up-to-our-challenges/article2001610/&quot;&gt;The Globe and Mail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mississauga.com/opinion/editorial/article/998443--tory-majority-means-strong-jobs-economy&quot;&gt;The Mississauga News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.montrealgazette.com/Gazette+View+Canada+needs+stability+majority+government/4701059/story.html&quot;&gt;The Gazette&amp;nbsp;(Montreal)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thespec.com/opinion/editorial/article/524311--a-decision-by-default&quot;&gt;The Hamilton Spectator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.insidetoronto.com/opinion/editorial/article/999234--editorial-conservative-majority-best-for-canada&quot;&gt;Inside Toronto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.macleans.ca/2011/04/29/the-ndp-surge-and-what%E2%80%99s-at-stake-in-this-election/&quot;&gt;Maclean&#39;s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2011/04/28/editorial-board-election-endorsement-conservatives-a-clear-choice-in-uncertain-times/&quot;&gt;National Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.insidehalton.com/opinion/editorial/article/998650--our-choice&quot;&gt;Oakville Beaver&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ottawacitizen.com/opinion/Editorial+board+election+endorsements/4673927/story.html&quot;&gt;Ottawa Citizen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ottawasun.com/2011/04/30/sun-backs-stephen-harper&quot;&gt;Ottawa Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theprovince.com/news/decision-canada/Editorial+Tory+majority+would+best+Canada/4693088/story.html&quot;&gt;The Province&amp;nbsp;(Vancouver)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thesuburbannews.ca/content/en/10060&quot;&gt;The Suburban&amp;nbsp;(Quebec)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thesudburystar.com/ArticleDisplay.aspx?e=3103202&quot;&gt;Sudbury Star&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.torontosun.com/2011/04/30/sun-backs-stephen-harper&quot;&gt;Toronto Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vancouversun.com/opinion/editorials/EDITORIAL+Conservative+majority+needed+through+turbulent+times/4701393/story.html&quot;&gt;The Vancouver Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therecord.com/opinion/editorial/article/523785--the-tough-choice-facing-canadians&quot;&gt;Waterloo Region Record&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.windsorstar.com/opinion/op-ed/Region+choice/4664064/story.html&quot;&gt;Windsor Star&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.winnipegfreepress.com/opinion/editorials/canada-needs-four-years-of-stability-121017189.html&quot;&gt;Winnipeg Free Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.winnipegsun.com/2011/04/30/sun-backs-stephen-harper&quot;&gt;Winnipeg Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Others                                                                      
&lt;ul style=&quot;line-height: 1.1;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nowtoronto.com/news/story.cfm?content=180408&quot;&gt;Now&amp;nbsp;(Toronto)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestar.com/opinion/editorials/article/983376--toronto-star-endorses-the-ndp&quot;&gt;Toronto Star&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vancouverobserver.com/blogs/centrist/2011/03/26/time-leader-we-can-trust&quot;&gt;The Vancouver Observer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ledevoir.com/politique/elections-2011/322281/elections-federales-d-abord-le-bloc&quot;&gt;Le Devoir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;double rightedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;margin-top: 25px;&quot;&gt;In total, in 2008, I found 20 papers that endorsed the Conservatives and 4 endorsing the opposition. In 2011? 28 and 4, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the Conservative Party of Canada has the best vision for the country, but seeing as only 37.65% to 39.62% of Canadians and 83.33% to 87.50% of newspapers thought so in 2008 and 2011 respectively, that&#39;s beside the point. The most substantive and quantitative indicator of right-leaning bias in Canadian news-media is the discrepency between those percentages - the percent of newspapers supporting right-leaning political parties and that of actual Canadians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these results, the myth of left-leaning news-media continues to remain.&amp;nbsp;If Canadian news-media is still left-leaning, it&#39;s putting on the greatest contortionist act of of all time. But it is not, and the myth remains because it&#39;s serves it&#39;s supporters in a couple ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;double leftedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supporters use the myth as a defense for shockingly disturbed views&lt;/strong&gt;. The more extreme the supporter, the stronger they prop up the myth. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/europe/seven-dead-as-bomb-rocks-norway-several-shot-at-youth-camp/article2106259/&quot;&gt;When the mass-shooting in Norway happened&lt;/a&gt;, readers at The Globe and Mail made their disturbed views known. The anti-Muslim tirades were to be expected sadly, but what was surprising was just how far they went. There were those condemning efforts to raise money for famine in Somalia as they believed it would help raise the next generation of terrorists. Unfortunately these comments were only removed from the article after it was discovered that the Muslim terrorist was a non-Muslim Norweigian. During the deletions, readers cited The Globe and Mail&#39;s &quot;left-wing bias&quot; propping up &quot;political correctness&quot;. Is it really political correctness at that point, or just correctness? Many of these same people frequently mention how they would like the CBC destroyed in any way shape or form, believing it to be the bastion of a liberal-dominated media. Now let&#39;s be honest, how &quot;left-wing&quot; can a broadcaster be when two of their most prominent personalities are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CHzCoUZG2Js&quot;&gt;Don Cherry&lt;/a&gt; and Kevin O&#39;Leary?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The myth scores political points for a political movement hellbent on being considered the underdog&lt;/strong&gt;. Canada&#39;s conservatives pride themselves on being a political movement fighting against the tyranny&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;double column left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of a systematic bias from all levels of society to do what&#39;s right for Canada. That the news-media bias has actually been in their favour this entire time, (as proven by the charts above) is of no concern. In fact, Canada&#39;s conservatives now control many of the institutions supposedly stacked against them, but why let reality get in the way of a good underdog story?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infact, why let reality get in the way of any story? &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/thank-you-bob-rae-for-stealing-my-plane-seat/article2105453/page2/&quot;&gt;Kenneth Harvey wrote a piece for The Globe and Mail criticizing Interm Liberal Leader Bob Rae&lt;/a&gt; for bumping him off a plane seat. Nevermind that Mr. Harvey wasn&#39;t allowed on the flight regardless of Mr. Rae, and that Mr. Rae was part of a frequent flyer program that guarantees him a seat (A frequent flyer program that any public figure or private citizen who flies around the country as often as Mr. Rae does is entitled to no less). If any of those facts were written in the article, there would be no story. All that mattered to Mr. Harvey, and The Globe and Mail, was that Bob Rae uttered that he was &#39;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aircanada.com/en/aeroplan/toptier.html&quot;&gt;Super Elite&lt;/a&gt;&#39;, the name of the frequent flier status guaranteeing him a seat. Good luck finding that detail anywhere in the article however, as if it was included, the article wouldn&#39;t be a smear job on one of the last of Canada&#39;s opposition to the right, and The Globe and Mail wanted a smear job. I pressed Kenneth Harvey on what I thought was journalism at it&#39;s very worst:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;double rightedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110810/left-leaning-news-medias-dead/tweets.300.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to laugh at the brash arrogance of Mr. Harvey, but one thought can&#39;t escape my mind: If this is the quality of &quot;journalists&quot; writing editorials for Canada&#39;s mainstream newspapers, perhaps the conclusion that news-media is right-leaning, or at the very least, not left-leaning is off target. Perhaps the real problem is that the notion of news-media with &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/News_International_phone_hacking_scandal&quot;&gt;any kind of integrity at all&lt;/a&gt; is what is really on the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/08/10/left-leaning-news-medias-dead.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/08/10/left-leaning-news-medias-dead.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Hikes, vol. 2</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quad&quot;&gt;Another month, another long weekend! If the last article didn&amp;rsquo;t get you jazzed to hike, well, this one probably won&amp;rsquo;t either, but you can enjoy the photos!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img style=&quot;margin-top: 30px;&quot; src=&quot;/file/post/20110729/the-hikes-vol-2/contents.png&quot; alt=&quot;In this issue: A Hiking Workflow, Chester Lake and the Three Lake Valley and Mount Fairview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width: 100%; background: url(/file/post/20110729/the-hikes-vol-2/summit.jpg) center top no-repeat; margin: 30px 0; height: 180px;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;quad leftedge&quot; style=&quot;float: left; clear: both; margin-top: 30px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quad&quot;&gt;So, you&#39;ve got a taste for hiking the rockies have you? Well one of the barriers to entry is finding interesting hikes to go on, and then figuring out how to do them. It often involves doing a lot of homework, but it doesn&#39;t have to be difficult. The internet is a great resource, but sometimes it just can&#39;t replace a good book, like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.ca/Canadian-Rockies-Trail-Guide-Patton/dp/0978237501/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1311966921&amp;amp;sr=1-2&quot;&gt;Candian Rockies Trail Guide&lt;/a&gt;, a bible of sorts detailing many of the hikes in the area (fig. 1). &amp;nbsp;However, that book lacks opinion, and some hikes may be far less interesting than others. You can supplement it with &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.ca/Dont-Waste-Your-Canadian-Rockies/dp/0968941974&quot;&gt;Don&#39;t Waste Your Time in the Canadian Rockies&lt;/a&gt;&quot;, a book that explains which hikes are worth doing and which aren&#39;t. This book has far less trails in it however, so it can&#39;t quite replace the usefulness of the Canadian Rockies Trail Guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quad&quot;&gt;Googling up trail names from the book to give yourself more information and reviews is a great idea, but you may discover a hike worth doing purely through the internet. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trailpeak.com&quot;&gt;Trailpeak.com&lt;/a&gt; is a good resource to find hikes, and I also like geeking out to &lt;a href=&quot;http://maps.google.ca/maps?ll=50.817215,-114.730225&amp;amp;spn=0.748769,1.783905&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;z=10&amp;amp;lci=com.panoramio.all&quot;&gt;Google Maps with Satellite and Photos mode turned on&lt;/a&gt;, clicking on areas and looking up names to find trails. I&#39;ve discovered a few quality hikes through that shot in the dark method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quad&quot;&gt;Once you&#39;ve identified a trail you&#39;d like to hike and know where to go, it&#39;s a matter of knowing how to stay on the trail you intend to. A GPS-Enabled smart phone (fig. 2) works well at this, though you will likely be out of cel signal coverage, so you will need to cache maps so you can look at them and your position without needing a cel signal. &lt;a href=&quot;http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/motionx-gps/id299949744?mt=8&quot;&gt;MotionX&lt;/a&gt;, is an app for the iPhone that allows you to select an area you&#39;d like to download the terrain map of for offline use. Of course, printing out a map or directions to stay on the trail is a must so your navigation doesn&#39;t rely on an electronic device that may die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quad&quot;&gt;You&#39;re all set! If you&#39;re too lazy to find a hike for yourself, I&#39;ve suggested another two excellent hikes for your enjoyment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 30px; float: right;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110729/the-hikes-vol-2/book.140.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig. 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110729/the-hikes-vol-2/phone.140.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Phone&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/fig2.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig. 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both; width: 100%; background: url(/file/post/20110729/the-hikes-vol-2/chester_lake.jpg) center bottom no-repeat; height: 1437px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; style=&quot;padding-top: 460px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=50.8052&amp;amp;lon=-115.2866&amp;amp;zoom=13&amp;amp;layers=C&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: -60px; float: left;&quot; src=&quot;/file/post/20110729/the-hikes-vol-2/chester_lake_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;ul style=&quot;float: left; margin-top: 60px; margin-left: 1em; padding-left: 1em; width: 480px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/instructions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Instructions&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=50.8052&amp;amp;lon=-115.2866&amp;amp;zoom=13&amp;amp;layers=C&quot;&gt;Park at the parking lot on the Smith-Dorrien Spray Lakes trail (about two hours from Calgary)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the logging road&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get on to the trail left of the logging road and proceed to the lake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the west end of the lake continue on to the trail to the valley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue on past the boulders and up to the valley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13 km hike depending on route, 4 hour hike&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure to continue on past the lake to the valley as the amount of views increases dramatically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width: 100%; background: url(/file/post/20110729/the-hikes-vol-2/fairview.jpg) center top no-repeat; margin-top: 120px; height: 1540px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; style=&quot;padding-top: 520px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=51.4071&amp;amp;lon=-116.2067&amp;amp;zoom=13&amp;amp;layers=C&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: -60px; float: left;&quot; src=&quot;/file/post/20110729/the-hikes-vol-2/fairview_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;ul style=&quot;float: left; margin-top: 60px; margin-left: 1em; padding-left: 1em; width: 480px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/instructions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Instructions&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=51.4071&amp;amp;lon=-116.2067&amp;amp;zoom=13&amp;amp;layers=C&quot;&gt;Park at the Chateau Lake Louise (about two hours from Calgary)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hug the lake&amp;rsquo;s south side, turning south on an asphalt trail after the canoe house&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the signs, ignoring the Paradise Valley trail and Fairview lookout options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue on the trail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the final ascent, taking care to spot the switchbacks just before the summit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 km, 4 hour hike&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&#39;s not a long distance hike, but the final ascent is a lot of elevation gain, take it easy on yourself and take your time with it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2011 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/07/29/the-hikes-vol-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/07/29/the-hikes-vol-2.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Hikes, vol. 1</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quad&quot;&gt;In case you haven&amp;rsquo;t noticed, it&#39;s nice out! And unlike last year, Alberta might just get a summer. With my attention turned to the outdoors, it&#39;s been tough to write about anything else. So I present you with guides and photography of my favourite hikes. If you&#39;re new to hiking and looking for tips or a push to get out and do it, in need of trail recommendations, or just like photography, you&amp;rsquo;re at the right place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img style=&quot;margin-top: 30px;&quot; src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/contents.png&quot; alt=&quot;In this issue: A Hiking Gear Guide, The Plains Of The Six Glaciers and Mount Indefatigable&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width: 100%; background: url(/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/plains.jpg) center top no-repeat; margin: 30px 0; height: 340px;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quad&quot;&gt;Before I tempt you with the prospect of seeing your Canadian Rockies in a way you might have never before, I should probably mention a few tips to get you started. Hiking sounds a little bit intense to a new comer, but all it boils down to is walking. If you&#39;re able to stand on two legs and move them around, you&#39;ve got what it takes. However, bringing some gear with you on these &lt;em&gt;walks&lt;/em&gt; will ensure no matter what happens on the trail, you&#39;re going to have a fun and safe time. Chance favours the prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;quad&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-right: 10px; float: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/pack.280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pack&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig. 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0 40px; float: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/shoes.280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Shoes&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/fig2.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig. 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 10px; float: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/spray.280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Spray&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/fig3.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig. 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;quad leftedge&quot; style=&quot;float: left; clear: both; margin-top: 30px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A light backpack (fig. 1)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;You need storage for your gear and your food! Ensure your backpack has a hip belt so it takes all the weight off your back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A hydration pack&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Store more water in less backpack-occupying-space than water bottles. The hydration pack allows for hands-free hydrating. Make sure you have at least 2 litres.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hiking shoes (fig. 2)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;A good pair will ensure comfort over the hike, and good grip is essential for safety. Waterproof strongly recommended so puddles don&#39;t turn your day sour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Layers&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;In addition to what you&#39;re wearing, bring an extra warm layer like a fleece, and a rain jacket and rain pants. Even in July you can get caught in a freezing storm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Layer accessories&lt;/strong&gt;: A toque and some thin fleece gloves will keep you warm should you get caught in a storm, and a bandana on your head soaked with water acts as a portable A/C unit in the burning mid day sun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bear spray (fig. 3)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Hiking in groups and making noise is your best anti-bear measure, but doesn&#39;t another line of defense seem like a good idea? Purchase a holster you can strap to your pack&#39;s hip belt so the spray is easy to reach, otherwise it&#39;s worthless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A first-aid kit&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Cuts, scrapes and blisters are a problem no more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emergency supplies (fig. 4)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;A compass, a whistle, an emergency reflective blanket, handwarmers, a swiss army knife, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VG4qI9YGKyc&amp;amp;feature=fvwrel&quot;&gt;a magnesium bar to start fires&lt;/a&gt; and water-purification tablets will allow you to survive the most extreme and implausible disaster scenarios. It&#39;s piece of mind that occupies nearly no space in your pack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hiking poles (fig. 5)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;While not required hiking gear like the above, poles keep hundreds (&lt;em&gt;thousands&lt;/em&gt;?) of pounds of pressure off your knees over the course of your hike, reducing wear and tear on a vulnerable part of your body. Poles ease grieving climbs and provide stability from slipping on the way down. Get collapsable&amp;nbsp;ones designed for hiking so you can attach them to your pack when you don&#39;t want them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 30px; float: right;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/supplies.280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Supplies&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/fig4.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig. 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/poles.280.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Poles&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/fig5.png&quot; alt=&quot;fig. 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both; width: 100%; background: url(/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/plains_hike.jpg) center bottom no-repeat; height: 1617px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; style=&quot;padding-top: 710px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=51.4061&amp;amp;lon=-116.2284&amp;amp;zoom=14&amp;amp;layers=C&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: -60px; float: left;&quot; src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/plains_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;ul style=&quot;float: left; margin-top: 60px; margin-left: 1em; padding-left: 1em; width: 480px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/instructions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Instructions&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=51.4061&amp;amp;lon=-116.2284&amp;amp;zoom=14&amp;amp;layers=C&quot;&gt;Park at the Chateau Lake Louise (about two hours from Calgary)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hug the lake&amp;rsquo;s north side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the signs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reach the Six Glaciers tea house&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carry on to the lookout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14 km, 4 to 5 hour hike&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good for all ages and skill levels, do it on a weekday to avoid crowds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;width: 100%; background: url(/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/indefatigable_hike.jpg) center top no-repeat; margin-top: 120px; height: 1335px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; style=&quot;padding-top: 335px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=50.637&amp;amp;lon=-115.1426&amp;amp;zoom=13&amp;amp;layers=C&quot;&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;margin-left: -60px; float: left;&quot; src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/indefatigable_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;ul style=&quot;float: left; margin-top: 60px; margin-left: 1em; padding-left: 1em; width: 480px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110707/the-hikes-vol-1/instructions.png&quot; alt=&quot;Instructions&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstreetmap.org/?lat=50.637&amp;amp;lon=-115.1426&amp;amp;zoom=13&amp;amp;layers=C&quot;&gt;Park at the Kananaskis Lakes parking lot (about two hours from Calgary)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk across the lakes from the lot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The indefatigable trail is on the right, it starts with some rocks blocking the path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigate through the trees until you walk along a ridge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At a fork in the trail, turn west to go up the mountain, or continue north to do a loop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 to 14 km hike depending on route, 3 to 5 hour hike&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take care near the top as it&amp;rsquo;s a little demanding. If the top appears too difficult, the hike is still extremely rewarding before the final ascent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/07/07/the-hikes-vol-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/07/07/the-hikes-vol-1.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Secondary Suites: Getting from A to B</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;triple leftedge&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calgary has been left in a very perplexing state by the decisions of city council. I speak of secondary suites. Secondary suites are a self-contained living space built into a portion of a house for rental purposes.&amp;nbsp;Currently they&#39;re not permitted in most of Calgary due to zoning restrictions. Only after considerable effort may you get the &lt;em&gt;chance &lt;/em&gt;to have your property rezoned for secondary suites.&amp;nbsp;I strongly support the broad rezoning of Calgary&#39;s residential areas to allow for legal secondary suites. It&#39;s a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;/20110428/higher-fees-lower-subsidies&quot;&gt;real way to create affordable housing&lt;/a&gt;, density and diversity in our neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;two triple&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the issue was first debated at city council earlier this year, I chose not to write about it because there were already a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rabble.ca/blogs/bloggers/apicazo/2011/03/secondary-suites-and-right-affordable-housing&quot;&gt;ton&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href=&quot;http://tylerkinch.com/2011/02/03/legalizing-secondary-suites-good-national-affordable-housing-strategy/&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.calgarymayor.ca/2011/03/most-calgarians-back-secondary-suites.html&quot;&gt;great&lt;/a&gt;-&lt;a href=&quot;http://bettercalgary.blogspot.com/2011/02/some-suite-yyc-facts-before-debate.html&quot;&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;in support of secondary suites. The support for them was almost &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.su.ucalgary.ca/topstory/2011/mar/official-secondary-poll-results&quot;&gt;overwhelming&lt;/a&gt;. Despite this, city council failed to rezone the city to allow for secondary suites. Actually, smaller efforts to rezone only specific areas near LRT and universities (which would seem like a slam dunk) failed, so no attempt was&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;even made&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;at considering zoning the city as a whole. As disappointing as it was to see the majority of aldermen vote against what Calgarians told them (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johnmar.ca/2011/03/04/alderman-mar-declares-pecuniary-interest-in-secondary-suites/&quot;&gt;or abstain from the vote altogether because they were building their own secondary suites&lt;/a&gt;), that&#39;s not why I&#39;m writing this article now. I&#39;m writing this because like I said, the current state of secondary suites in Calgary is now completely perplexing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;indent&quot;&gt;City council more recently did decide to zone areas of Calgary for secondary suites. What is perplexing are the areas they chose to zone. Zoning communities next to LRT that can support higher density? No, that would make sense. Instead &amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/calgary/story/2011/04/18/calgary-secondary-suites-allowed-edge.html&quot;&gt;secondary suites will only be zoned across the board in all newly developed communities&lt;/a&gt;. Density will be encouraged in the areas farthest from the city&#39;s core. Where Calgary struggles the most to serve transit to its citizens and provide proper infrastructure are the only areas in which citizens will be permitted to have multiple dwellings within the same house. It&#39;s a completely perplexing policy, and easy to see why it is a bad one. But how did it get this way, and how do we get out of it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;triple leftedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110609/secondary-suites-from-a-to-b/quote.png&quot; alt=&quot;The only thing that can turn Calgary&#39;s communities into slums is a disparity amongst them&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;triple rightedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re stuck with bad secondary suite policy because of the reasoning of two very different groups of Calgary&#39;s aldermen: the aldermen that support a broader rezoning of Calgary&#39;s residential areas to allow for secondary suites, and the aldermen that don&#39;t. When the motion came up to allow for secondary suites in new Calgary communities, these two very different groups came together to pass it. The supporters of Calgary-wide secondary suites saw this as an opportunity to get closer to that goal, and those against Calgary-wide secondary suites saw the vote as an opportunity to justify their reasoning. Opponents concluded a broad rezoning would outrage Calgarians that bought into neighbourhoods expecting no secondary suites were permitted. This reasoning is flawed on two accounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assumes secondary suites are actually a problem. (I say &#39;actually&#39; because secondary suites can be a problem when illegal and unregulated, as many will continue to be if the city refuses to zone for them).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assumes most Calgarians actually know how their residential area is zoned and what that zoning permits or doesn&#39;t permit before buying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;two triple&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opponents of secondary suites simply don&#39;t want secondary suites &#39;in their backyard&#39; but don&#39;t want to admit to this pettiness. Perhaps these aldermen desire a Calgary of gated communities where you&#39;ll never have to see another Calgarian unless you choose to, but that&#39;s not what the majority of Calgarians want.&amp;nbsp;I think many opponents of secondary suites oppose it for an irrational fear it will turn Calgary&#39;s communities into slums. The only thing that can turn Calgary&#39;s communities into slums is a disparity amongst them, which is exactly what now exists on paper with the poor policy settled on from aldermen on both sides of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;indent&quot;&gt;Though the new communities that are now permitted for secondary suites will be many years away, we need to make sure we move Calgary off this path and towards secondary suites for all communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secondary_suites_in_Canada&quot;&gt;Cities across Canada&lt;/a&gt; have already rezoned for secondary suites to great results, yet Calgary remains behind. This is the exact same conclusion I reached in regards to &lt;a href=&quot;/20110526/open-data-why-you-want-it&quot;&gt;Calgary and Open Data&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;- other cities move forward and establish positive results yet we ignore the facts because of too many dinosaurs on city council, out-of-touch with Calgarians and unwilling to listen. Think I&#39;m exaggerating? Alderman Dale Hodges wished the secondary suites discussion &quot;would just go away&quot;. Bluntly put, Alderman Hodges wants Calgarians to stop caring about the issue so he will no longer feel under some sort of an obligation to listen. Unfortunately for Alderman Hodges, this issue won&#39;t go away, especially not in it&#39;s current failed state. City council will revisit zoning the city for secondary suites in December. Calgarians are ready for our city to go from A to B, Calgary&#39;s aldermen should finally take note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/06/09/secondary-suites-from-a-to-b.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/06/09/secondary-suites-from-a-to-b.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Data - What It Is and Why You Want It</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Did you see The Social Network movie? Do you remember that scene in which there is a &quot;hackathon&quot; where eager students do a random hacking assignment to score an internship with Mark Zuckerburg&#39;s Facebook? Well, the City of Calgary has the opportunity to do that on a much larger scale. Except without the drinking. Or the internship. The more I think of it, what the City has the opportunity to do bares little resemblence to that scene, except for the most important part: like Mark, the City can tap the potential of geeks at little expense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-top: 320px;&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;triple leftedge&quot;&gt;Now I don&#39;t mean &#39;geeks&#39; in any kind of deregatory sense. I mean in it the so-passionate-about-a-specific-area-of-expertise-you-dedicate-disgusting-amounts-of-time-to-it-and-struggle-to-hold-conversations-with-regular-people-because-your-knowledge-is-so-intense-in-the-awesomest-way-possible sense. You know what I&#39;m talking about. Chances are you are a geek too (you are at this site after all!). I think all of us probably have an unhealthy dedication to something that sets us apart, whether we geek out to The Social Network style computer hacking, environmental sustainability, business management, geological formations,&amp;nbsp;blog writing, astronomy, chinchilla manicuring, or bananas. I realize some of those examples aren&#39;t quite like the others, but the point is that we are all specialists and we all bring something to the table. I&#39;m certain someone, somewhere, is looking to manicure a chinchilla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110526/open-data-why-you-want-it/header1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Setting Calgarians Loose On Calgary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;triple leftedge left&quot;&gt;So, if we&#39;re all geeks, how can the City of Calgary set us loose for the benefit of our fair burg? Well, it&#39;s called &#39;open data&#39;. If you haven&#39;t heard of it before, you&#39;re going to hear a lot about soon enough, starting now. Open data is the release of information that people are allowed to freely browse and use in an unrestricted, or somewhat-unrestricted, manner. If you read this far and found the concept of open data completely underwhelming, it&#39;s because you haven&#39;t stopped to think about it yet. Governments collect and manage a&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;lot&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;of data. So much so that I chose to bold the word. Things like road closures, bus schedules, soccer field bookings, property values, food safety inspections, the list goes on and on. If the City owns a chinchilla, they have data on everything there is to know about it. His name is Joey. At least it would be if there was one and I was in charge.&amp;nbsp;If you&#39;re &lt;em&gt;still &lt;/em&gt;not excited about having access to this data, try dreaming up some practical applications of its use: a daily email of the latest road closures, a mobile app for bus times, a website to find available soccer fields, analysis of what neighbourhoods are rising in property values relative to others for investment, Open Table or Urban Spoon showing food safety grades of restaurants, etc. My ideas are small potatoes compared to what could be dreamt up as data is made available and brighter people start using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;triple rightedge left&quot;&gt;Now, there is no Facebook internship to win if you use this data to a better end than your contemporaries, so why would any one bother? Well, if the data is open and unrestricted, there&#39;s absolutely no reason to not make a profit from wielding the data into a service Calgarians are willing to pay for. But many will also volunteer their time to non-profit applications of the data for the same reason &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wikipedia.org/&quot;&gt;Wikipedia &lt;/a&gt;isn&#39;t empty. We are geeks, and when we find ourselves with a little time and have stumbled upon something we&#39;re passionate about, we might just contribute. The level at which we tend to contribute increases as barriers are removed and the process is made easier. So as data becomes more available and accessible from the City of Calgary, our use of it will explode. Even though Calgary hasn&#39;t yet launched an open data resource, there are already die-hards doing great things with what is available. Take &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/gordonmcdowell&quot;&gt;Gordon McDowell&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; tapping of City Council feeds to create a robust online archive of our municipal government in action (as explained through his super genius baby):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;triple leftedge left&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/TYoZa-6QrcM&quot; width=&quot;460&quot; height=&quot;292&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;triple rightedge left&quot;&gt;Gordon McDowell, who I haven&#39;t yet had the pleasure of meeting, is a videographer and programmer geek - which I of course mean in the most nicest non-deregatory way - he&#39;s a specialist. He&#39;s also a prime example of why all of us should want open data, even if few of us will use it. All of us are busy people with demanding lives, but for those of us who won&#39;t get around to using open data should it be come available, there will be the few that do, and we want to make sure we give them that opportunity. Gordon shares his specific genius to demonstrate how the city can provide their own archived council video for next to no cost, a cheap technical solution our municipal government likely wouldn&#39;t have stumbled on without his expertise. Not only can great new solutions be imagined from tapping Calgary&#39;s data, but as Gordon&#39;s council video example shows us, our municipal government can be opened up and made far more accessible to all Calgarians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110526/open-data-why-you-want-it/header2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A Cost Effective Way Of Doing The Impossible&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;triple leftedge left&quot;&gt;Open data does the impossible - it creates open governments and engages citizens. It is a tool in creating better government and it&#39;s ridiculously cost effective as well. A little money needs to be invested to make Calgary&#39;s data available online in a sortable and parsible way, but the result is that instead of only city council and some public servants looking at the books, all Calgarians would be encouraged to. That&#39;s right, every geek out there, whether a chinchilla expert or computer scientist, could poke around and identify new and better solutions to the city&#39;s problems that may otherwise have been missed. Someone may identify a more cost effective way to deliver the city&#39;s website, or to manicure Joey the chinchilla. Instead of complaining about the actions of city council, you could apply your knowledge to helping them do a better job. Or if you&#39;d still rather just complain, at the very least supporting open data allows other Calgarians the opportunity to help our city do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;triple rightedge left&quot;&gt;Open data is already happening around us. &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.edmonton.ca/&quot;&gt;Edmonton&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;http://data.vancouver.ca/&quot;&gt;Vancouver&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.toronto.ca/open&quot;&gt;Toronto &lt;/a&gt;and many&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Data_in_Canada&quot;&gt;other jurisdictions&lt;/a&gt; have begun opening their data. Even the federal government is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.data.gc.ca/default.asp?lang=En&amp;amp;n=F9B7A1E3-1&quot;&gt;stepping up to the plate&lt;/a&gt;, though &lt;a href=&quot;http://eaves.ca/2011/03/17/canada-launches-data-gc-ca-what-works-and-what-is-broken/&quot;&gt;they are working out some ideological issues with the word &#39;open&#39;&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;It&#39;s time to use technology to take government forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2011 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/05/26/open-data-why-you-want-it.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/05/26/open-data-why-you-want-it.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Instant Gratification Suicide</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;two quad&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a stroll down my most dreaded of store aisles: the dental aisle. Of all the things I buy, toothbrushes might be the most frustrating. I&#39;m paralyzed by choice. Soft or medium? Tongue brusher thingy or rubber grip handle? Angled bristles or a brush-life indicator strip? There&#39;s so many features presented in that aisle that despite beginning my brush shopping experience frustrated by how much choice there was, I leave even more frustrated that I still couldn&#39;t get my exact dream toothbrush (not that I dream about these sorts of things). The floss section has no such excess of choice. Infact there used to be a choice in that section that is now strangely absent: Reusable flossers. I used one as a kid as it made flossing really easy for this little tyke, and it didn&#39;t need to be thrown away each day (well, except the floss you tie to it each night of course!). It was a great product, yet I can&#39;t find it in stores anywhere today. Apparently I&#39;m not the only one who can&#39;t find them, as flossing die hards the world over are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Butler-Flossmate-Handle-12-Pk/product-reviews/B000S75OEC/ref=cm_cr_dp_all_helpful?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;showViewpoints=1&amp;amp;sortBy=bySubmissionDateDescending&quot;&gt;resorting to ordering them online&lt;/a&gt;. So what&#39;s pushed the reusable flosser out of the market? Non-reusable flossers! They come in giant packs of a hundred or so, cost next to nothing, and save you that arduous 3.7 seconds you&#39;d otherwise waste wrapping your floss around a reusable flosser or your fingers each night. You use it and toss it in the garbage immediately after. No fuss, no muss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except there is a ton of muss. Flashback to 1942. Midway Atoll - a tiny set of reefs and islets - serves as the site of the decisive turning point for the Allies in the Pacific theatre during World War II. In 2011, Midway once again plays host to a turning point in the pivotal conflict of our generation. Except this time, we&#39;re losing. The Great Pacific Garbage Patch, an almost indeterminably large water column saturated with plastic debris, occupies a swath of ocean encapsulating Midway Atoll. It&#39;s not as graphic as you might imagine, but that&#39;s what makes it worse. Although there is large debris like plastic bottles, or say, &lt;em&gt;dental flossers&lt;/em&gt;, you don&#39;t need an icebreaker to get through it. The real danger lies with what&#39;s unseen, plastics breaking down into the tiniest bits of polymers, nearly impossible to clean up and&amp;nbsp;perfect for consumption by the smallest marine life to rise up the food chain to us. This has widespread negative biological consequences that we are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cbc.ca/documentaries/doczone/2008/disappearingmale/&quot;&gt;just starting to understand&lt;/a&gt; (perhaps this article should be titled &#39;instant gratification castration&#39;). This is but one example of the real, undeniable and unpoliticizable damage our need for instant gratification causes us - the muss of our disposable flossers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hate waiting. We hate it so much, it&#39;s become the enemy of our generation, and we will stop at absolutely nothing to destroy it. Economic certainty? It often takes a backseat to our desire to not wait. Gas prices are at all time highs, causing the cost of food and essentials to rise around the world, and yet I&#39;ve seen people idling their cars with the same frequency as ever. Whether these idlers agree with the sentiment or not, they want our gas prices even higher if only to save themselves the inconvenience&amp;nbsp;of the 0.4 seconds to start the engine. Environmental catastrophe? We no longer have to save up the money to make purchases, or wait for things to be delivered and &lt;a href=&quot;/20101219/ifad&quot;&gt;consequently everything has become disposable&lt;/a&gt;. We chuck out things we buy in favour of newer models as fast as we buy them. Very little has longevity any more, and it&#39;s not just limited to our purchases. The&amp;nbsp;well being of our society takes a pounding from our refusal to wait. We maintain our personal relationships often in the fastest ways possible inviting friends out via a mouse click or a text message. How often do we find ourselves not even responding? Bands rise and fall in popularity with the click of a mouse on iTunes, and while many probably should fade away, there is a ton of great music today, probably more now than ever. But will we ever look back at today&#39;s music the way we look back at the music of the past if we jump from album to album within days? While it&#39;s debatable any of these societal examples are a bad thing (and I could certainly argue for the opposite), one thing is clear: this is a new cultural shift. Instant gratification is turning us into the disposable generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our society is changing, and with it we are bringing about unnecessary and avoidable economic and environmental problems. Remember waiting for stuff? &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thewildernessdowntown.com/&quot;&gt;The Arcade Fire touches on this sentiment quite well&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(wait, &lt;a href=&quot;http://whoisarcadefire.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;who are they?&lt;/a&gt;). Waiting for things was tough, but it brought about the sense that things were &lt;em&gt;worth&lt;/em&gt; it. And when they weren&#39;t? Our memories of waiting would often be the best part.&amp;nbsp;Patience is a virtue for many reasons, not least of which is that we might just make our actions that much more reponsible if we give ourselves time to. So stop and smell the roses - it just might be one of the best things you do to ensure they&#39;ll be around for others to smell too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/05/11/instant-gratification-suicide.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/05/11/instant-gratification-suicide.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Higher Fees? No, Lower Subsidies</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;double three first column&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bigletter&quot;&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;algary has many suburban communities. Many &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;suburban communities. They pop up so fast, it&#39;s hard to keep track. &amp;nbsp;Symons Valley, Silverado, Wentworth. I&#39;ll forgive you if you&#39;ve never heard of these communities. Many of them are generic and uninspiring, unwalkable and unattractive. And communities like these continue to spring up in the farthest reaches of Calgary&#39;s borders. The sprawl of our city from the geographic footprint of these communities is Calgary&#39;s greatest problem. The sprawl is socially and environmentally unsustainable, and as bad as that is, it is even more damaging economically, sending our city into a mire of debt as we continue pouring public money into strained transit and infrastructure to support these communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;double three column&quot;&gt;Calgary also has many citizens who believe in the power of the free market. That a market where supply is bought and sold at its true cost, bereft of government intervention, is beneficial for consumers and retailers alike because environmental, economic and social abuses will be phased out by market forces. I have argued, and will continue to argue that the benefits described aren&#39;t possible when market forces favour short term greed over long term solutions. As such I favour smart government regulation and targeted investment that considers the big, long-term picture, to steer the economy away from problems before they happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;double three column&quot;&gt;The issue is this: the City of Calgary is proposing developers of these new communities start footing more of the bill for their development. Developers make new neighbourhoods on the edge of the city, and it&#39;s up to the rest of Calgarians to pay for servicing that community with things like roads, transit, water and sewage. As it stands now, developers pay a small fee per house to the City to cover these costs, but the fee isn&#39;t anywhere close to recovering the expense, so Calgary plunges into debt. Regardless of your support for government involvement in the market, or their absence from it, I will tackle this issue from both perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot; style=&quot;height: 150px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/file/post/20110428/higher-fees-lower-subsidies/choices.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;triple leftedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;double&quot;&gt;If you favour a free market, it&#39;s time to get beind what you stand for. The fees Calgary charges to developers need to go up, because they are not fees, they are subsidies, and they are too high. I had the chance to debate with Ric McIver on this issue a week before the Calgary Mayoral election. He fancies himself as a free market guy, yet he doesn&#39;t support ending these subsidies. Why would he go against his convictions on this issue (other than the fact &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ricmciver.ca/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/McIver-Campaign-Contributions-18Oct2007-to-24Sept2007.pdf&quot;&gt;developers subsidized his election campaigns&lt;/a&gt; to the tune of hundreds of thousands of dollars)? Well he told me that the problem with eliminating subsidies to developers is that they&#39;d pass on their increased costs to home buyers. He said because we don&#39;t live in a vacuum, home buyers would flock to bedroom communities like Airdrie and Chestermere, and we would no longer get their property taxes. He may be right about all of that, except for suggesting any of that is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;double&quot;&gt;What is a &amp;nbsp;problem is that Calgary never receives enough from the property taxes of these new communities to cover the cost of building and maintaining infrastructure for them. So for every home built on Calgary&#39;s outskirts that attracts someone to pay their property taxes here, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ffwdweekly.com/article/news-views/news/15-billion-reasons-to-talk-about-subsidizing-sprawl-6361/&quot;&gt;we are at a net loss&lt;/a&gt;. In other words, it&#39;s more economically damaging for us to attract new Calgarians to the outskirts of town than have them not live here at all. If we respect the free market by removing these subsidies, we can save our city&#39;s economy and not artificially lower the cost of urban sprawl below what it&#39;s market value should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;triple rightedge left&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;two double&quot;&gt;If you favour smart government investment like I do, these developer subsidies are the wrong choice. Calgary&#39;s problems with sprawl are well documented: sprawl strains our police and fire coverage, our transit and infrastructure, the city&#39;s budget and our property taxes. We want to invest in solutions to those problems, not their cause. Even worse, these new communities are often poorly designed, unwalkable and come with their own set of problems. Often their only saving grace is their artificially low cost, which only exists because all Calgarians are paying to have it that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;two double&quot;&gt;We need to provide affordable housing, but subsidizing the cost of homes only the outskirts of the city isn&#39;t the way to do it. If we send lower income Calgarians to the boonies, provide strained infrastructure and transit to them, and break the city&#39;s economy doing it, we will cripple our city and set a course for turning our suburbs into slums. Affordable housing isn&#39;t an incentive to bringing in new Calgarians if the city tears itself apart to do so - they have affordable housing in Detroit, but people aren&#39;t moving there. There are many measures we can take to create affordable housing in Calgary that don&#39;t break the bank: Secondary suites, density, transit oriented development and mixed income neighbourhoods, yet these are issues many Calgary alderman have voted against. We need to stop pandering to developers and start subsidizing smart growth that helps alleviate problems with our city, not create them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;double three first column&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bigletter&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;he argument is framed wrong by many. The City has not proposed to hike the levies that developers must pay -&amp;nbsp;the City is considering lowering their subsidies to developers. Developers should no longer rely on the taxpayers&#39; dime to make their communities artifically cheap in order to turn a profit - they will now have to focus on creating liveable communities that people want to buy in to. So whether you believe in a free market or a regulated one, or could care less about markets and just want Calgary to be the best city it can be, these developer subsidies aren&#39;t the answer, and you need to make sure city council knows you feel that way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2011 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/04/28/higher-fees-lower-subsidies.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://calgaryurbanite.com/2011/04/28/higher-fees-lower-subsidies.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
